Stanford
University we'll move on and talk about
um cosmology and what string theory has
to offer uh
cosmology I suppose I could spend two
minutes just um telling you what I think
the accomplishments and the failures of
string theory of
Bin uh I think we'll do that another
time it's getting late and we want to
get on with some uh some
substance all right let's uh go back to
the special theory of relativity for a
moment and just remember what it's all
about it's about thinking of space and
time as a single entity that we call
SpaceTime and space time has a
geometry the geometry is described by a
metric let
me I think I better leave it
on
um it's described by a metric a metric
tensor special relativity in special
relativity the metric is especially
simple and the metric is just if we take
two points in space and time two
neighboring points in space and time can
you see them
no it doesn't matter but let's take two
points in space and time any two points
in space and time they're separated
let's call this the x- axis let's call
this the T
axis and there's two more axes coming
out of the Blackboard uh these are two
arbitrary but neighboring points and
they're separated by
some DX
DT Dy
DZ separation here and we Define A New
Concept the New Concept is the
relativistic distance between them the
proper time and the proper time is
defined to be DT
^2 minus 1 over the speed of light
squared the X2 + the y^ 2 + d z^
2 different than you might have written
down if this were ordinary ukian
four-dimensional space if it were ukian
four-dimensional space you probably
would have put a plus sign here you
certainly would have put a plus sign
there and you might have left out the 1
/ c^ 2 although the 1 / c^ 2 is just a
rather arbitrary Factor you could always
get rid of it by
rescaling uh the space dimensions or the
time Dimensions appropriately in other
words by choosing units for space and
time in which the velocity of light is
one you can always do that let's leave
it for a
moment this is
the proper time between two points along
the
trajectory it's a nice concept as long
as DT is bigger than dx2 plus d y^ s
plus d z^2 you the proper time the
square of the proper time in particular
ought to be a positive thing but notice
that if dx2 + d D y^2 + dz^2 is bigger
than dt^ 2 something bad happens to this
expression namely d^ 2 is
negative but never mind nevertheless
this is the definition of proper time
between any two
points uh the more the most important
thing for us tonight is how light rays
move how do light rays move let's
suppose a light Ray passes through those
two
points then the rule the rule for a
light wave let's forget the X the y^ S
and DZ s for a moment let's just take
the x s
here so the light Ray is moving along
the
x-axis little infinite tmal
uh separations along the light Ray have
only a DX and a DT the rule about light
rays is that along the trajectory of a
light Ray the proper time is
zero somebody traveling with a light Ray
if you could which you can't uh would uh
discover that the clock stands still
which is another way of saying that the
proper time along the trajectory of a
light wave is zero so if you want to
know what kind of
trajectory a light Ray consists of you
simply
set the left uh the right hand side of
this equal to zero so this is equal to
zero for a for the trajectory of a light
Ray
and another way to say the same thing is
that the t^2 well all right c^2 D t^2 is
equal to the
X2 I just multiplied by c^2 and uh that
transposed one side to the
right or taking the square root it says
that
CDT is equal to
DX or what's the other
possibility or
CDT is minus
DX this is just another way of saying
that a light wave moves with a speed of
light that DX by DT that's the velocity
of the light Ray is equal to C or DX by
DT is minus c one of the light rays with
the plus sign moves to the right the
other light Ray with the minus sign here
moves to the left all right the main
point here is just that the way you
diagnose a geometra
geometry like this to find out how light
rays move is you solve the
equation that says uh that the proper
time along the light trajectory is zero
all right now we're going to come to the
more
complicated uh geometries of general
relativity in general relativity the
metric is more complicated it varies
from place to place the geometry varies
from place to
place and it's described described by a
more
complicated object the metric tensor
which itself can vary from place to
place and we've done these things before
so I assume you know a little bit about
it you have a metric tensor GI well
let's call it g mu
new just remember our notation mu and
new are variables which run over the
four
dimensions of space time usually we take
them to go from 0 to three zero being
time and X1 X2 X3 being the ordinary
components of
space the S squ is G mu new times DX mu
d x
new X mu and X new are the coord the
four coordinates of
SpaceTime and as always in an expression
like this it it is automatic that we sum
over the repeated index here there are
two repeated indices so this stands for
things like g d t^2 x is
t plus
G1 DT DX blah blah blah blah blah all
possible
combinations with their metric
coefficients again if we want to know
how a light Ray moves we
simply in other words if we want to find
the little
infinitesimal gaps that correspond to a
light Ray moving from one to the other
we set this equal to zero that's the
rule we set that equal to
zero and that gives us
constraints on uh on the allowable
trajectories of light rays that's the
content incidentally of saying that
light rays move with a speed of light
whether the speed of light is one or C
or if you use some other units uh
something
else d that doesn't matter the invariant
statement is that light rays move on
trajectories of zero this should be D
squ excuse
me
trajectories which correspond to zero
proper time all right now we're going to
to do is we're going to examine a
particular metric it's a metric of a
black hole we're not going to solve
Einstein's equations we're just going to
write down the answer and we're going to
inspect it for a while and uh learn
about
it tonight I'm going to only spend a few
minutes with the metric showing you
basically one property about the way
light rays move in that
metric but we're going to get right to
the point tonight about the quantum
mechanics of black holes the quantum
mechanics of black holes is very strange
in some ways it's very strange and in
some ways it's extremely ordinary in
fact it's very strange how ordinary it
is uh given how bizarre black holes are
as classical non-quantum mechanical
entities okay so let's write down let's
just explicitly write down the metric
first let's write down the metric of
flat space
I'm going to set from here on in I'm
going to set the speed of light equal to
one in that case what I would write down
for the metric of flat space would
be DT ^2 minus dx2 + d y^ 2 plusus dx2
minus d y^ 2 minus dz^2 all right let's
write it minus D y^2 minus dz^2
or this
way now this here is nothing but the
ordinary metric of ordinary flat ukian
space here and we can write it another
way we can write it in polar coordinates
let's think about polar coordinates for
a moment polar coordinates are the
coordinates that I would use if I'm
standing in the center which I am I'm
always at the center I'm very
self-centered all right and I'm always
at the center and instead of using
coordinates X Y and Z I'm going to use
coordinates which are the distance from
me R let's call it R the distance from
me and two
angles to represent uh the direction uh
that I might be examining so R and two
angles in fact the two angles are are
often summarized
by the symbol Capital
Omega that symbol actually stands for a
unit sphere a unit sphere why a unit
sphere because I can think of myself
surrounded by a unit sphere and then a
point on the unit sphere determines the
direction the symbol Omega often stands
for a unit
sphere and the symbol D Omega
squared stands for the the metric on the
unit
sphere maybe we should write down the
metric on a unit sphere to just be
really concrete to represent the unit
sphere you need two angles what are they
called um aimal and po uh polar angles
or longitude and latitude okay two
angles Theta and F and the metric of the
unit
sphere is the length element on the unit
sphere is just the Theta squar Theta is
the polar angle Plus plus
sin^2 Theta d^
2 that's the metric on the unit
sphere f f is the angle around the pole
and Theta is the distance along an
angular distance from let's say from the
North Pole or maybe it's a no I think
this is actually are the distance from
the
equator and this is the thing that's
usually called called just just um
abbreviated it's just an abbreviation
it's called the Omega squared and it
means the metric of a two-dimensional
ordinary two-dimensional sphere but of
unit length if the sphere had some other
unit radius if the sphere had some other
radius then the metric the metric of it
would simply have the square of the
radius multiplying the whole thing but
we're going to be drawing a unit sphere
yeah okay no let's let's put in what
happens if the radius of the sphere is
not one if the radius of the sphere is
not
one then we would write R 2 where R is
the radius of that sphere times d t
Theta 2 + sin^2 Theta d^ 2 or just R 2 D
Omega squared okay so R 2 The Omega squ
is the metric of a sphere of radius r
now I stand at the center and I look
around
me and I see two points they're
separated you could think of them as
separated by an a DX and d y and a z but
no I'm going to think of them as
separated by a d a d Theta and a
DF okay the r different different
distance to me different angle and so
forth what's the distance between those
two neighboring points
the distance between those NE
neighboring points in ordinary flat
conventional space in other words the
thing which really replaces this thing
this piece of it in polar
coordinates it is the r
s
plus that's the difference in radial
distance along those along uh the radial
distance and then a contribution coming
from the distance uh in angular space
and that's just this plus r 2 The Omega
s Shield s sh i l
d
yeah the question with Shi whether
there's a t or not and there is no
t
d no no
T okay no no I mean in in the middle
before before the
the Z yeah oh no I don't think so
shield shield yeah there
isn't okay
um how does this get
modified in the presence of a black hole
here's a black
hole some coordinates and we're going to
describe the metric again in polar
coordinates it's a nice round
object nice spherically symmetric object
polar coordinates of the the convenient
coordinates to write it in terms of in
fact that's generally true when you have
something which has nice spherical
symmetry then polar coordinates are
usually the best coordinates to describe
it in okay so how do we do what's uh
first of all if we go very far from the
black hole the influence of the black
hole should be
um should go should uh fade should fade
As you move away that's the first thing
that means that far from the Black black
hole this should be pretty good all
right I'll write down the answer and
then we'll just check
that the answer is one minus now black
hole has a mass let me just write down
over here what variables are interesting
is the mass of the black hole
M there is something that we call the
either the schwat shield radius or the
radius of the
Horizon all right we can call it R subes
that's for Schwartz Shield or Schwarz
Shield
and that happens to be related to m is
twice
mg and just once I will put the speeds
of light in after that we'll set the
speed of light equal to
one C I may I may I may here and there
decide to put the C's back in just for
illustrative
purposes uh but if I write that R
Schwarz Shield is 2
mg you know that I'm setting the speed
of light equal to one all right so
it's uh 2
mg over c^2 little r now little r is the
radial
coordinate little r is the radial
coordinate we
can in Brackets we could also write this
as 1 minus
r schwar Shield over R the ratio of the
distance to the point where r little r
here is the point of Interest our
Schwarz Shield is the radius of the
Horizon we're interested in points far
from the black hole for a moment or at
least out Beyond the Horizon of the
black hole so little r is bigger than
Big R
here all right that gets multiplied by
dt^
2 replacing this now this looks good
when little r gets big and we go far
from the black hole this becomes this
here becomes small and we just get back
our one the
t^2 then there's
minus the same thing except in the
denominator 1 - 2
mg over c^ 2
R times the R
2 again when little r gets large the
denominator becomes one and this just
becomes the r s and then the last term
here that's easy just plus r^ 2 The
Omega
squar this is the metric of a schwar
shield black
hole memorize
it it's a great thing for uh for
cocktail parties and you
know last term has a sign also yeah
thank you good good for you
all right and 2 mg over c^2 is just our
short
Shield oh the mic follow
okay
okay all right so let's erase off the
Blackboard what we don't
need now when you look at this you see
something a little bit
strange 1 - 2mg if little r is
large this is
small and what's in here not only is
close to one but even more important
it's
positive what's here is also positive so
we haven't done anything really weird
like changing signs of coefficients and
so
forth uh but notice that something
unusual does happen at the point where R
gets small enough that this gets bigger
than one where does that happen that
happens you know what from here on I'm
going to get rid of the C squares
they're only going to confuse me I'm
going to forget about them just let's
get rid of them set c equal to
1 where is the crossover where this gets
bigger than this and that happens when R
is equal to 2
mg something happens when r or when 2
mg/ R is equal to 1 same thing when R
becomes smaller than this
you're inside the black hole you're
inside the schz shield radius at R
equals to 2 mg something really weird
happens the coefficient of dt^ 2 becomes
zero sounds like no
time no time when the coefficient here
is zero the proper time from one value
of time to a neighboring value of time
is just zero right and even worse the
coefficient of Dr s gets infinite it
sounds like something rather dramatic
happens at the horizon or at the Schwarz
Shield radius of the black
hole and we're going to come back to
that we're not going to analyze that
tonight tonight we're
uh we'll uh we'll just take this metric
and say all right something interesting
is happening in Ral
2mg but there's another place where
something interesting is happening I
don't know interesting uh
uh weird and that's at R equals 0 at r
equal 0 not only is this negative but
it's also
infinite likewise this thing has some
nasty behavior in
it so at R equals
z some kind of singular Behavior happens
and at Ral 2mg some kind of other kind
of singular Behavior happens they're
quite different they're extremely
different they they have very little
relationship to each other I can tell
you right now what the difference is if
you were falling into a black hole well
whenever you're falling into a
gravitational object you experience
tidal forces everybody know what tidal
forces are anybody not know what tidal
forces are okay you experience tidal
forces uh and if you're big enough the
gradient of the gravitational field
pulls on you differently in different
parts of your body your feet are pulled
harder than your head so you get
stretched uh you're also squeezed inward
to some extent those are called tidal
forces and you can feel them of course
you wouldn't feel them jumping off a
diving board because you're too small by
comparison with the uh the scale over
which the gravitational field of the
Earth
changes but um if you fell into a black
hole you would feel a tidal
Force the tidal Force at the Horizon is
finite and as the back hole gets bigger
and bigger and bigger the tidal Force at
the Horizon gets less and less and
less so nothing dramatic would happen
you wouldn't get sque if it was a
sufficiently big black hole you don't
get squished at the Horizon of a black
hole and we're going to work that out
we're going to see that you don't get
squeezed like toothpaste into the uh
into the black hole perfectly uh benign
place to fall into as we will see even
though the mathematics looks uh like
something fairly bad happens on the
other hand at R equals z that's where
you would really feel
pain that's where the tidal forces
become infinite that's where um all hell
breaks loose and
um the nasty Place rals 0 is called The
Singularity Ral 2mg is called The
Horizon okay let's talk about light rays
now let's talk about a light Ray moving
radially outward at some angle on the
sphere in other words along uh maybe
along the North Pole of the sphere or
the East pole of the sphere or the South
Pole of the sphere some pole of the
sphere some some Direction on the sphere
the light Ray is moving radially outward
that means along the right light Ray
there is no change of the angles the
angle as I shoot the light Ray out the
angle is constant that it's moving in
and so along the lightray D Omega squ is
zero DT is not zero along the light Ray
As you move from one point on the
lightweight to the next time changes a
little bit not proper time but what
orary time and also the radial distance
changes so you're watching the light Ray
you have your clock you see a little bit
of DT and a little bit of d r how does
the light Ray move what's the equation
what's the what's the rule for the light
Ray the rule for the light Ray is that
along light Ray the proper time is zero
so let's work that out it's 1 - 2
mg dt^ 2
must equal I'm
setting this we don't need to worry
about I'm setting the rest of it equal
to zero and I'm doing that by setting
the DT ^2 equal to the Dr 2 term equals
1 / 1 - 2
mg over R the R
2 that's the motion of a light
Ray we can multiply both sides of the
equation by the thing in the denominator
here and that just squares this and
removes
this and now I can take the square root
if I like it just says that Dr the
distance along the radial direction that
it moves is equal to 1 - 2 mg /
R
DT if you're far if you're far away from
the black hole the this is close to one
and it just says Dr is equal to DT of
course if I put the speed of light back
in there would be a speed of light here
and it would say that Dr is equal to C
DT but that's just a statement that the
light Ray moves with the speed of light
in fact the whole statement is really
the statement that the uh that the light
Ray moves with the speed of light but
you can see that as you move in closer
to the black hole the mathematical
description of the motion of the light
Ray gets modified a little
bit and in fact let's divide by DT let's
divide by
DT oh incidentally I did take a square
root didn't I yeah so that means there
are two
possible solutions one corresponds to an
outgoing light Ray and the other
corresponds to an infalling light Ray
those are the two branches of the
solution but let's take the uh let's
take the outgoing light Ray
and if you want the ingoing light Ray
you just change the sign
okay this of
course is the time rate of change of the
radial coordinate we could call it the
velocity we could call it the Velocity
in our in the particular coordinates
that we're using the rdt that's the rate
of change of the radial coordinate with
time and that's equal to 1 - 2 mg / r as
I said far away nothing unusual but what
happens when you get in very very near
the um let's not worry about the
singularity tonight let's only worry
about the
Horizon at the Horizon 1 - 2 mg / R goes
to zero R becomes equal to 2 mg at the
Horizon and 1 - 1 is zero so very close
to the
Horizon the light rays slow down they
slow down the closer you get to the
horizon slower they move
outward and right at the Horizon the
light rays don't move at all they just
sit there static and they don't move at
all so we could draw a picture of this
let's draw time here's
time let's draw R this
way and at some value of R namely Ral 2
mg let's put that in over here that's
the Horizon of the black
hole okay that's the Horizon of the
black hole and now what happens to let's
take outgoing light rays when we're far
away Dr by DT is close to one that means
the light Ray on this diagram moves with
close to the
45° axis here but what happens is we get
closer to the black hole as we get
closer to the black hole the light rays
move much more slowly
in a given amount of time they move a
smaller
distance being upright here means moving
slowly and as you get very close to the
Horizon the light rays hardly move at
all and right on the horizon the light
rays just stand
still or the light rays that are trying
to get out just stand still okay so they
don't get out
anything that's inside the Horizon we
haven't analyzed it in detail but let me
tell you what happens inside the Horizon
inside the Horizon all light rays
whether you think they directed outward
or not you're falling into the black
hole you try to send a light Ray out or
you try to send the light Ray in exactly
well not exactly the same thing but in
either case the light rays fall inward
right to R equals 0 where R equals 0 is
where the singularity is light rays that
originate inside the black hole simply
cannot
Escape light rays that originate close
to the Horizon take a very very very
long time to
escape light rays right on the horizon
just sit there and light rays far away
do what light rays do uh in uh if there
was no black hole there
okay so that's the basic
framework of the Schwarz Shield black
hole that's really all there is to it
there of course a lot more to it and
we're going to do a lot more
but could you clarify the statement the
light slows down and what
exactly
yeah just that statement I thought the
speed light was invariant
that's R that's
T yeah I understand
that the rule that light rays move with
a speed of light is depends
on what is the speed of light 3 * 10 to
the E something but if I change from
centimeters to meters or meters to
centimeters becomes 3 * 10 10th or or
meters to kilometers it becomes 3 * 10
5th uh what's going on here is effective
As you move into the black hole there's
kind of a a moving change of
units R is being measured in different
units at different places but but the
real point is the real point is there's
a universal statement about the speed of
light and it's that along a light Ray
the proper time is zero that is what
replaces the statement that the speed of
light is 3 * 108 m/s
for all speeds of light all light rays
move the same
way they move on what we call a null
trajectory a null trajectory means that
the proper time along the trajectory is
exactly
zero that's the universal statement for
all light
rays which is in special relativity
becomes the statement that they all move
with the speed of light and that stands
true for regardless of the medium that
it's trans
no no that's in a vacuum right that's
could you draw an incoming light R again
on the right there yeah okay first of
all I drew an outgoing light R and an
outgoing light R just sort of started
very close to the Horizon here it's
sticks it doesn't want to go anywhere
and then eventually it goes off the in
the incoming light rate does just
exactly the opposite it starts to fall
in and then asymptotically gets closer
and closer to the Horizon never quite
getting
there so one lesson is that even a light
Ray that shined in toward the
Horizon takes an infinite amount of this
kind of time here what's called
coordinate time it takes an infinite
amount of coordinate time to get to the
Horizon because of the Slowdown
effect okay so we have now the basic uh
setup and I actually want to jump from
the geometry of a black hole which we're
going to come back to it's very
interesting and many many uh things to
explore about it in particular the most
interesting of what of which is to
explore the nature of the Horizon what
kind of thing is the Horizon what kind
of funny kind of thing is going on at
the Horizon is anything funny going on
at the Horizon we are going to explore
that we're going to explore the question
how do you make a black hole but we'll
come back to this later what I wanted to
really jump into for tonight and maybe
for next time is the quantum mechanics
of black holes black holes are
objects now the question is are they
objects like any other kind of
object or are they something new and
special which violates the laws of
physics I'll remind you what uh
Professor
Hawking said about black
holes he made a claim and a claim was a
very well-reasoned claim an extremely
well-reasoned
claim he said that anything that
falls onto the surface of a black hole
he said anything that falls into a black
hole we will come to the question
whether things do or don't fall into
black holes looks from this point of
view that it takes an infinite amount of
time to fall into the black hole this is
a contentious question that uh it's not
contentious it's a subtle question that
we'll come back to but for the moment
let's just think about things which fall
onto the Horizon of a black hole in this
sense
here
they they get closer and closer and
closer to the
Horizon and uh they sort of get stuck on
the horizon from the point of view of
outside they don't get back out if they
don't get back out that means that all
the information that they brought into
the black hole is
lost to the outside observer in the form
of either depending on WE we'll we'll
discuss it later but depending on
whether you envision it as falling into
the black hole or just progressively
closer and closer to the Horizon of the
black hole it becomes unavailable to the
outside all right that's not such a bad
thing you just say well okay but the
information of what fell in is simply
getting closer and closer to the Horizon
no big
deal it's not not it hasn't disappeared
it hasn't gone anywhere it's just gotten
squeezed Tighter and Tighter onto the
Horizon the problem is as we're going to
see tonight or tonight and partly next
time there reason not a reason it's it's
extremely uh complete consensus about it
black holes in time evaporate if black
holes in time evaporate then the
question is what happened to all the
little itsy bitsy bits of information or
whatever it is that fell onto the
Horizon does it just disappear out of
this
world or is it somehow uh stored inside
a little tiny remnant of the black hole
it refuses to disappear or does it get
radiated out with the evaporation
products exactly what happens this this
was a big puzzle in physics but before
we can address the puzzle
and it was string theory in part which
largely resolved
this um before we do that we have to
understand why people thought that black
hole why people think that black holes
evaporate now a black
hole is the most
dull object in the
universe if
you create the black hole and leave it
for a while it settle settles down to a
perfectly
spherical totally uninteresting object
nothing comes out of it it's totally
black totally black in the sense that uh
that no light comes out of it and it's
very
uninteresting uh you can't get messages
out of it or anything else but it turns
out not to be quite
true black holes are not as um dead
let's call them dead dead in the sense
uh that uh that they are infinitely cold
infinitely um what should we
say infinitely black black has two
meanings incidentally black can either
refer to the emit emits no light at all
or it can refer to the idea that it
emits black body radiation black body
radiation is thermal radiation heat
radiation so let me just black holes are
black in the sense that they emit heat
radiation it was thought earlier that
black holes were black in the sense that
they emitted no
radiation so we need to come to an
understanding of what it was that made
um Hawking beckenstein other people
think that black
holes uh have some heat in them they're
not completely dead they have some heat
and because they heat they have some
heat they glow
because they glow they give off light
because they give off light or radiation
they give off energy that means with
time their energy must
decrease well energy and mass are the
same thing equal
mc^2 and so with time the mass should
decrease as it gives off this radiation
and if the mass
decreases then the schat shield radius
to mg decreases and one should expect in
time if black holes really do have
some active uh th active heat in them
that eventually they will simply
disappear because they'll radiate away
all their energy and if that happens as
I said there's the puzzle of what
happened to everything that fell in
basically
okay to
understand and we're not going to do any
fancy mathematics of studying Quantum
field theory in the background of a
black
hole
uh to really understand the concepts you
don't have
to and um I don't feel up to teaching an
advanced course in Quantum field theory
in curved space tonight it would take
more than one night so we're going to do
something simpler we're going to go
through beckenstein's arguments about
why black holes have to have
entropy now first before we talk about
why black calls have entropy let's talk
about entropy in general what is entropy
and uh how do you define
it we can Define it either with
Precision or we can Define it
qualitatively I prefer to Define it
qualitatively to understand what entropy
is you need to understand what
information is and let me be very very
simplest simplistic about what
information
is information you can in the
information about a
system the information about a system
let's not ask about what it is but how
do you quantify it how much information
is there in a
system or better yet how many how much
information separates one system from
another what's the uh what's the way
that you ex what's the way you explain
to somebody the difference between
systems well
you ask a bunch of questions about the
system I'm not even going to try to to
ask the qu well yeah we could we could
uh we could here's a system here's a
system it's a big box the box is broken
up into little
boxes those little boxes are about as
big as an
atom and you can know everything about
what's in this box if I tell you yes or
no whether there's an atom I I would
have to tell you what kind of atom but
let's simplify it
uh let there be just one kind of atom in
the world and either a box is empty or a
box is full if I go
through the boxes and tell you whether
there's an atom there or not I have told
you just about everything about that box
there's an atom here there's an atom
here there's an atom here there's an
atom here there's an atom here here here
here no other atoms well then there's a
block or a lump of stuff in the
middle okay maybe that one's missing now
it's a lump of stuff where with a funny
shape so you can go through this thing
with a bunch of yes no questions is
there or isn't there an atom in this box
that box and so forth another way of
describing information is to say if I
want to describe the system what I need
to do is give a code to describe it and
the code might simply be a series of
zeros in ones where you go through this
thing 0 0 0 1 0 1 1 0 in other words it
could be a long binary
digit how long well it depends on how
many bits of information you're trying
to describe how many yes no questions it
takes to describe a system
completely the number of yes no
questions or the number of binary digits
that you would have to prescribe to
describe a system or to distinguish it
from other systems is called the
information in the system
um information theorists use it all the
time and as I say they characterize it
in terms of bits a bit is a yes no
question okay and um okay
so the quantity of information is
characterized by the number of bits in
this system here the number of bits
would just be the number of boxes the
number of boxes where you might or might
not have a um
an atom that's pretty clear I mean we
could describe everything in this room
by by breaking it up into sufficiently
small
boxes if we didn't want to deal with the
fact that there are different kinds of
elements we could break it up into even
smaller boxes and simply ask whether
they're well I suppose we would have to
distinguish electrons from
quirks but we could always break it down
into into yes no questions
uh is there a quark in this box isn't
there a quark in this box is there an
electron in this box isn't there an
electron in this box and eventually we
would learn everything there is to know
about this room by asking that series of
questions the minimum number that it
would take to describe the room and to
distinguish it from every other room
would be the quantity of information
that uh describes that room if that's an
a static
situation no it could be it could be an
instantaneous uh disc
yeah yeah yeah at a moment of time at a
moment of time right
right another fact information never
disappears this is a basic uh idea in
physics it's probably more basic than
anything else and the meaning of that is
the following that if you start with two
different
configurations two different
configurations let's say here's one
here's another
one they're fairly similar as a matter
of fact they just have a couple of atoms
out of
place uh but they're different they're
distinct they're distinguishable
distinct and uh and you can do an
experiment in principle to tell the
difference between them then if you let
them run run means let them evolve with
time they will stay different of course
will change relative to what they
started with this one might move to here
this one might move to here and so forth
but if you start with two distinctly
different configurations they stay
different okay they don't run into each
other for example you never have a
situation where as you run these things
they will evolve to the same
configuration that's a very very B
that's such a deep rule of physics that
people forget to State it when they're
stating what the uh what the law a
physics
are that the amount of information that
it takes to describe a system is
constant in
time and that
the distinctions between
systems never
disappear okay now
sometimes it looks like information
disappears you
drop a series of water molecules into
your
bathtub and you might drip them in in
some very very
specific
way you might drip the drops of water in
with a morse code messages on them two
different uh two different bathtubs full
of
water and one of the messages uh uh I
don't know some great literary
Masterpiece and the other one some other
great literary masterpiece being coated
in the dripping of the
foret and those two bathtubs full of
water started out differently okay they
sure look the same after a few
minutes after a few minutes you let that
water settle down and they sure look the
same but that's only because you don't
look carefully enough if you could look
carefully enough at every single
molecule in those bathtubs you would
find that
the configurations of them stay the
same we might say that effectively
information doesn't disappear but it
gets hidden it gets hidden because after
just because of it gets hidden by the
fact that there are just so many degrees
of freedom and they're so small that you
can't see them that in effect
information which is there is
effectively lost L just because it's
stored in degrees of freedom which are
too small and too numerous to keep track
of so in practice in a sense information
does disappear but not in
principle there's a notion of hidden
information information that's
inaccessible to you for one reason or
another now of course the notion of
inaccessible Can Depend just on how good
your uh your ability to study and
manipulate the system is it might depend
on how good your microscope it is it
might depend on how quick you are in
your ability to measure molecules and so
forth but subject to whatever
limitations there
are there's a notion of inaccessible or
hidden
information what is
entropy the simplest statement of
entropy is that it is the number of
hidden bits of information the number of
things which in principle are there to
distinguish things but which are just
unavailable to you because they're
stored in things which are too small and
too numerous to keep track
of uh so in the case of this bathtub
full of water so the only thing I really
care about is how hot the bathtub is I
don't want to burn myself when I get in
I want to make sure there's enough water
in the bathtub that I can take a nice
bath uh I want to what else I want to
make sure it's water not hydrochloric
acid um but you know there's a handful
of things that I want to know about that
water and furthermore there's a handful
of things that I can know about the
water the amount of energy that's in it
that in the form of its thermal energy
the fact that it's water and uh and a
few other
things and that's a pretty much complete
description of the water well the water
might have ripples on it I don't care
much about the ripples when I'm taking a
bath but nevertheless I could see the
Ripples and I could distinguish uh the
fact that the bathtub was filled up 5
minutes ago than half an hour ago but if
you wait a while even those ripples go
away and there's not even any ripples on
the surface to tell you any detailed
information it's all hidden in the micro
structure of the
molecules so all that information is
hidden information and it's called the
entropy that's what entropy is the
number of bits of information which are
unavailable now there are more technical
definitions but for the moment I think
that uh that that is good enough for us
incidentally
uh entropy and energy are the basis for
thermal
dynamics normally
when you learn thermody Dynamics or
statistical mechanics particular
thermodynamics you start with the idea
of temperature temperature is a highly
derived
concept right well you know it's what
you measure with a thermometer very
simple yeah what you measure with a
thermometer is a very very highly um uh
evolved uh thing it's easy to measure
but it's very hard to
define the definition of temperature
what is the definition of temperature
anybody know the definition of
temperature no of course you don't
because the definition of temperature is
a highly contrived thing not not so much
contrived it's a it's a um a um what's
the right way a derived concept derived
from the ideas of entropy and
temperature okay so I'm going to tell
you now all right we have energy I
assume we all know what energy is and we
have entropy now let me give you an
example entropy might be the the amount
of hidden information in the
atmosphere okay I'll tell you right now
what temperature
is I have to write an equation first for
myself just so I get it right
okay temperature is the change in
entropy of a system if you add one bit
of information to
it if you CH now here's here's an
example I'll give you an example of
where this comes up you take your
computer your computer is full of bits
of information the bits are stored
individually in the form of uh in the
form of what
um
bits yeah I mean whatever uh some little
thing inside the computer is either
switched on or switched off and that's
your yes or no question now your
computer is full
of information that you put in
there supposing I want to get rid of a
bit of
information in other words I want to
eliminate some I'm not going to
eliminate the circuit I just want to set
it back to its original uh starting
point I want to take the computer and
you know reboot it just to get it back
to its original starting configuration
in that case I will lose a lot of
information all the information that's
in the computer well let's not go that
far
let's just erase one bit of information
if you erase one bit of information I
just told you it's impossible to erase
bits of
information that's uh that's a basic law
of physics what really happens is that
bit of information whatever it is is
displaced from inside the computer to
out into the atmosphere the distinction
between one configuration of the
computer and another configuration which
differ by one by one bit that
distinction gets taken from the computer
into the
atmosphere so that the atmosphere
becomes a little bit different by one
bit of
information uh than it was before you
erased the
bit that process of transferring a bit
from the computer into the atmosphere
heats the
atmosphere adds a little bit of energy
to the atmosphere it's in inevit able
heating that happens because you erase
bits from your
computer what is the energy that's
transferred to the uh to the atmosphere
when you transfer one bit the answer is
the temperature that's the definition of
temperature the
change in the energy of a system when
you add one bit of
information to it is called the
temperature you could write this another
way way you could write the change in
the
energy when you
change the number of bits Let's uh by
some
number is the temperature times the
chain well okay let's let's let's um
let's slow
down notation for entropy we need a
notation for entropy I don't want to say
entropy every time and I don't want to
write the word entropy on the Blackboard
and equations we need a symbol for
entropy the standard symbol for entropy
is
s s is
entropy okay now what I told you is that
the
change in the energy let's call it Delta
E when I add one bit that
means when Delta s when Delta s is equal
to 1 if Delta s is one unit then the
amount of energy that's get added to the
system is called the
temperature what happens if you add two
bits for the at to the
atmosphere then the energy of the
atmosphere changes by twice the
temperature what happens if you add
three bits three times the temperature
what happens if you add s
bits then the change in energy is T
times the change in
entropy the change in in energy is
proportional to the number of bits that
you transfer to the atmosphere or that
you transfer to anything a b up full of
hot water in other words it's the change
in the energy when you hide a certain
number of bits of information when you
remove them from someplace and hide them
in your uh in your whatever it is you're
hiding them in in your heat bath
basically this is a basic formula of
thermodynamics
extremely confusing formula if you start
with temperature as the basic
concept but it's a very simple concept
if you start with entropy is the basic
concept then temperature is I said the
energy that you add when you add one bit
and this is usually written
differentially DS uh sorry D equals
TDS this is one of the fundamental laws
of thermodynamics
the change in energy is the temperature
times the change in
entropy that's the definition of entropy
hidden information stuff that you can't
easily see can I uh I did a calculation
comparing a change in entropy of a hard
drive if you erased it 100 GB and how
much that triat would be for a glass of
water it's about 10us 15° oh is it
that that that's that small of a change
of temperature you race how much about
100 gabes of of of information from hard
drive yeah it's it's very yeah a bit a
bit of information at an ordinary room
temperature that's room temperature is
very low for one thing at room
temperature yeah at room temperature
right so room temperature in any kind of
reasonable other units is very
small and yeah a bit it is a very
typically a very small amount of energy
at the at the ordinary
temperatures are you using the computer
hard drive as an analogy or are you
actually saying no no no that's a real
fundamental law of
computers that's um oh who land hour's
land land hour's uh rule about the
Eraser of
information because when you erase a bit
of information on a hard drive you're
not actually erasing anything that it's
still there you're just setting it from
a high
no no erasing it means what erase you
haven't erased the object which held the
bit all right but let's say you here's
what you're going to do you're going to
whatever the configuration of the
computer is you're going to turn that
bit to
off so that so you will have forgotten
what was there because you turned it
off in that sense you've erased the
knowledge that that that that little
circuit had
you've uh and eventually you could turn
off your turn off by by rebooting the
computer or by starting the computer
over and bringing it back to the
configuration as when you bought it
there's nothing left in that computer
that remembers what you did to it so
you've erased it right you've erased it
and uh the number of bits that you've
erased in other words the number that
you brought back to neutral
is the change in the entropy of the
computer and that or if you like that's
the number of bits that had to be taken
from the computer put into the
atmosphere and uh that's what uh what
you calculated when you calculated the
real thing is much more
inefficient yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah that's right that's right right you
do a lot of other stuff besides erase
the bit
normally like you rub your finger on the
on the keyboard and all kinds of other
useless uh stuff right does that say
that a at high
temperatures hiding one bit of
information cost more energy costs more
energy yes well or right we'll heat we
heat the system well we'll um increase
the energy of the heat bath by more the
higher the temperature the
more energy you will be putting in when
you hide that bit yeah that's that's
exactly what it
says but but in a sense uh that's the
definition of the
temperature so it's a question of horse
before the cart or cart before the horse
yeah if you
write on top of a previously existing
bit and you have lost the information of
what that bit was yes that changes the
inter yes that that's
it changes the amount of information it
decreases the amount of information in
the uh in the computer but that
information cannot disappear out of this
world so you wound up putting it into
the atmosphere but it's hidden in the
atmosphere and so it's
entropy okay that's the basic idea of
entropy why my teacher didn't teach me
that when I studied thermodynamics in
1959 I don't know 56
uh I went around asking my colleagues
when you teach statistical mechanics do
you teach that and basically what I
found out is none of my colleagues knew
it not
good information H hidden information
hidden information
right the computer scient the computer
scientists all know it but there were no
computers back then right
yes yes yes but these ideas that's right
but these ideas go back to boltzman
these ideas are older than computer
science actually there was quite no all
right in statistical mechanics and in
physics they go back to boltzman in the
19 century in um computer science they
go back to the 40s
Shannon Claude Shannon was the one who
uh formulated these ideas okay enough
history
um okay so now let's let's talk about
the
information that's hidden in a black
hole as I said you can either think of
it as hidden in the black hole or you
can think about it as hidden on the
surface of the black hole you keep
throwing stuff into the black hole and
it accumulates closer and closer to the
Horizon in some sense and becomes
unavailable it'ss all smushed up onto
the onto the
Horizon uh it takes light forever and
ever and ever to get out of the
Horizon so it's effectively
lost Why did
beckenstein Why did
beckenstein
um think that black holes had
entropy well I'm going to tell you the
way I think about it but it was also the
way beckenstein thought about it but I'm
going to tell you why he thought there
was entropy by Computing the entropy uh
by Computing the amount of information
that you can store in a black
hole what I'm going to do is Imagine
building up the black
hole by throwing bits of information
into it and I want to know after I have
thrown in a certain number of bits of
information how big is the black hole
the logic is very very similar to asking
how full will a bathtub
be if I fill it by dropping in atom by
atom and I tell you after in
atoms how big how full will the bathtub
be well the way you figure it out is you
say an atom has a certain
volume every time you drop an atom in it
adds to the volume of the water and if
you in and each each differential drop
changes the uh the volume by a little
bit and raises the level of the Water by
a certain amount so if you want to know
how high the water will be for a given
number of drops what do you do you just
count how much will the water be raised
by dropping in one
drop of course you don't have to be that
dumb you could be smarter than that but
that would be one way to do it just drop
by drop by drop
and discover each drop that you put in
has a certain volume therefore it will
raise the water a certain amount after
end drops the water has a certain height
we going to do the same thing by
dropping in bits of information to form
a black hole we can start with a small
yeah how does how does throwing in you
know phons electrons chairs relate to
throwing in information okay so we're
going to we're going to come to that but
um basically we're going to we're going
to throw something in which we're pretty
sure has no other information in it
other than the question of whether it's
there in in there or
not in other words we're going to fill
this black hole up by a series of
processes for which each one of them has
no other information stored in it other
than
that a photon went into the black hole
you can simply ask did the photon go in
or didn't the photon go in that's a yes
or no question and uh yeah you live in
coordinate time right so it'll an
infinite amount of time for that
information get into the back but it
doesn't take very long for it to get
squashed onto the Horizon where it
becomes an unavailable yeah
right spin up or spin down yeah that's
another example or the polarization of
the photon the polarization of the
photon is it's either up or down along
the xaxis so it's one bit of information
but you have to be careful uh and here's
what you have to do all right so we
going we're going to start let's take a
black hole there's a black hole it has
mass
m it has radius r or the Horizon has
radius R which is twice
mg we've already made it we've got it
there now we want to throw in one more
object and that should be the simplest
possible kind of object for which we can
simply ask is it there or is it not
there one bit of
information let's think of it as a
photon all right but we have to be
careful if we throw in a photon from
here let's suppose this black hole is a
kilometer in
radius and we throw in a photon along a
beam of laser light where the photon has
a wavelength which is you know some
microscopic wavelength then there's a
lot more
information in that Photon in the
arrival of that Photon than just whether
it got in or not for example did it come
in from here did it come in from here
did it come in from
here the angle on the horizon where it
arrived from that's uh clear really
going to there may be a lot of bits of
information in describing the angles to
various amounts of
precision so throwing in a photon is Not
By Any Means necessarily the same as
throwing in one bit of information
there's a lot more information you know
you could ask you could begin a yes no
question as follows is it in the upper
hemisphere that it came in yes okay is
it in the upper half hemisphere to to
the right or no okay it's to the left
and now imagine dividing up the uh The
Horizon of the black hole and asking a
series of yes no questions until you've
localized where that Photon came in to
the maximum degree that it can be
localized it can't be more localized
than its
wavelength it's fuzzy out to its
wavelength but it's clear that there's a
lot more yes no questions you can ask
about that Photon coming in and so that
photon is not one bit of information
it's a lot of
information
unless you do something to that Photon
or you deal with a photon which is so
uncertain about where it is cuz photons
are always uncertain they don't have any
brain but uh unless in principle there
is an uncertainty uncertainty in the
sense of
Heisenberg unless there is a maximal
amount of uncertainty
about where that Photon entered the
black
hole now what does that mean in practice
in practice that means that the
wavelength of the
photon the wavelength of the photon is a
measure of how delocalized the position
of the photon is in quantum mechanics
we're talking about quantum mechanics
now if the wavelength of the photon is
as big as the whole black hole hole then
when that Photon arrives it arrives in a
way where there's complete uncertainty
about where it entered from so the first
thing you want to do is you want to work
with photons which have the longest
possible wavelength but can still get
into the black
hole is there a
restriction on not being able to get
into the black hole yes it's a fact that
can uh that's been known know basically
from classical physics that if you shine
light on a black hole of wavelength
longer than the size of the black hole
it just reflects off it will not go
in only wavelengths which
are no longer than the radius of the
black hole Horizon have any chance of
penetrating through to the
Horizon so what's the best you can do
you can work with photon
whose wavelength is comparable to the
radius of the black hole they are so
uncertain in their location that you
can't tell where they enter the black
hole on the other hand they're short
enough wavelength that they can get into
the black hole so you're working just on
the margin on the edge where the photon
will go into the black hole but where it
will provide no other information other
than it either got in or it didn't get
in okay so let's add add a photon to
this black hole you ever worry about
which direction I mean it seems like
that's more information well it it it
really isn't if the wavelength is very
long because the the wavelength is is so
long that the electric field is varying
very slowly across the black hole and it
doesn't matter which direction it comes
in from but uh but you're right to ask
the question but I think the answer is
no that if the wave length is long
enough uh that it doesn't uh it doesn't
provide any information
okay good so we want to send in a photon
of wavelength
Lambda equal to 2
mg now first question what is the energy
of such a photon we're going to add
we're going to be adding some energy
now here's this business that uh that
whenever you uh hide a piece of
information you wind up adding a little
bit of energy to the system that you're
hiding the information in so how much
energy have you um hidden inside the
black hole or how much energy have you
added to the black hole the energy of
the
photon so we'll just write down a
formula or two about energies of photon
I'll write down just to remind you the
energy of a photon or any light
wave is equal to the speed of light
times its momentum p is the momentum of
the
photon now what's the connection between
momentum and
wavelength anybody
remember H bar over Lambda H Plank's
famous
constant all right this is because we're
dealing with
photons because in quantum mechanics
information is quantized into
photons uh this is a real Quantum
problem we're going to see where H bar
winds up it'll be interesting to see
where H bar winds up in this formula all
right so what's the wavelength the
wavelength or the M uh the momentum is
HR over
Lambda Lambda being the wavelength the
shorter the wavelength the higher the
momentum so now we can say that the
energy of the photon that we threw in is
the speed of light time Plank's constant
/ Lambda is it is it h over Lambda or H
bar over Lambda bar which is the same as
H over Lambda oh I'm not I'm not keeping
track of two
pi's it's h bar over Lambda isn't it
yeah it's h bar over Lambda H Lambda
that's a the energy is H I
can't it is C * P that's not important I
I don't care about two pies let's let's
forget two pies not important order of
magnitude energy is CH H over
Lambda and
uh yeah p is um p is H H Bar times the
wave number and there's a 2 pi you right
there's a 2 pi okay but there this H
over lamb not important H over
Lambda um the energy is H over Lambda
now
Lambda we're going to be choosing equal
to the to the uh to the size of the
black hole so now we can write out that
the energy that we've put
in apart from factors of two I'm not
interested in factors of two here we
can't this calculation is not going to
be that precise with within a factor of
two all right so the energy that we're
adding to the black hole is the speed of
light times plunks constant divided by
m/ G and that adds
one bit of information to the black hole
now I could stop right here I have now
told you how much information it cost
how much energy it cost to hide one
bit what have I told you temperature the
temperature here's the temperature of
the black hole c h over
mg that's the Hawking temperature
another there are some factors of four
and pies and things that we're not going
to get right by this little argument but
uh let's let's let's go a little bit
further this is one bit of information
that we put in let's see how much bigger
it makes the black hole let's see if we
can see how much bigger it makes the
black hole it makes the black hole
bigger because when you add energy you
add Mass eal
mc^2 all right so E = mc²
so this can also be written
as the change in the mass let's call it
the change in the mass time c^
2 the energy that I added goes into
increasing the mass and it changes the
mass by this formula here let's clean up
the formula a little
bit let's divide by c^ 2 and that winds
up putting the C in the denominator
here that's the change in the mass
that's the minimum change in the mass
when you add one bit of
information is HR over mg okay let's go
a little further let's calculate the
change in the radius of the black
hole let's calculate the change in the
radius of the black hole how do I do
that I do it because I know that the
radius is proportional to M * G so I
just multiply
I multiply both sides of this equation
let's see am I doing am I um yeah by G
where oh this was uh yeah this was the
wavelength
downstairs so we multiply by
G and this is a change in the radius of
the black hole let's see where um
did I do that
right the wavelength over the Schwarz
Shield
radius HC over the Schwarz Shield radius
is the change in
energy that's Delta
E eal
mc² so if I want the change in mass I
think I want to divide it by
c^2 the change
mass is equal to c h no is equal to H
over r
c
agreed have I confused you
thoroughly okay good that's the change
in mass and now if I multiply it by G it
gives me the change in
radius this is the change in radius of
the black
hole okay so every time I throw in one
bit of information I change the radius
by an amount which is inverse to the
radius
itself with the uh GH over
C I really think I've lost some C's but
I'm not sure where well maybe
not up where oh oh oh you're right
you're right you're right the Schwarz
good good good the Schwarz Shield radius
is not mg it's mg over c s that's where
it went mg over c^
s so I think this should be by now C
cubed if I'm not
mistaken
H that's that's where you you set
everything like Cal one yeah that's
don't set c equal one in part of a thing
and not the other part yeah I think it's
yeah I think it's g h over RC cubed
that's the change in radius now
multiply by the
radius R times the change in the
radius what's R times the change in
radius
RDR that's Dr s right the
change in R SAR apart from a factor of
two is 2 R
Dr just Elementary calculus so R * a
small change in R is proportional to the
change in the square of the
radius but what's the square of the
radius the square of the radius of the
Horizon is the area of the Horizon so
look what this formula says it says
every time you drop a bit of information
in you change the area of the Horizon by
a universal amount
which doesn't depend on the mass of the
black hole it doesn't depend on the
radius of the black hole at the instant
that you did it you always wind up
changing the area by the same amount
it's kind of like saying that every time
you drop a drop into a bathtub assuming
the bathtub had nice straight walls that
you always raise the level of the
bathtub by the same
amount and it doesn't matter how full it
is is you always raise the volume by the
same amount in this case you increase
the area of the black hole by one unit
where unit means the area GH over C
cubed okay this is a very small
area every small area is the square of
some every area is the square of some
length of course so this is the square
of some length
it's the square of the square
root this quantity has units of length
Let's uh it's it's the plunk length it's
called the plunk length and it's very
small let's see if we can estimate
it Okay g in ordinary um units units
means
um uh kilog M seconds G is about s about
7 * 10 10-
11th how about plunk
constant I think uh well that's H bar I
think is that H or H bar six I don't
remember another seven H is H is 105
okay 7 * 10us
34 that's this and C Cub that about C
Cube we have the square we're going to
take the square root in a minute but
what's the square of the speed of light
the cube of the speed of light cube of
the speed speed 27 *
10 to the
24th all right so we got
a 27 * 10 what did I say
24th okay we got a lot of small numbers
upstairs and a lot of big numbers
downstairs this is a very small number
uh I think it's about 10 to Theus uh
68th or 69th or something like that 10us
69th square m or something like that I
don't remember exactly okay I happen to
remember it's 10 to
Theus 66 or 66 some's about that square
cm 681 and over - 69
okay the plunk length itself the square
root of this is about 10us 35 CM so it's
smaller than anything that you can uh
access in any way in experimental
physics and what it says is every time
you drop a bit on the bits I mean the
way to think about it is the bits are
impenetrable and they stick to the
horizon
in no finite amount of time do they ever
get past the Horizon they stick to the
Horizon they have sharp elbows and they
simply push the other ones out of the
way each one occupying about a plunk
area I have a question if the first one
was sent in and it's approaching Horizon
now the next one comes in the Horizon
moves out well it pushes it pushes the
other ones out of the way and it makes
the area bigger in the only way to make
the area bigger is to make it bigger so
it doesn't just increase the radius in
now it's the prior one is inside that's
not not inside it's on no no no no they
they they never get past the Horizon
even if you added a huge mass to to like
two colliding black
holes it's hard to believe the next one
that come yeah yeah that's we we'll
we'll um we'll go through a bit of that
we have to Define what the Horizon is in
a careful
way uh we have to define the precise
concept of a horizon which we have
haven't done yet we've only uh
yeah um this would not probably is
significant but on a a the
area what you're saying the a plank left
square is a plank area on a flat surface
butere a shle surface
so so for your 8 uh
km uh diameter black hole
your wavelength that you want for this
photon is 8
km right Long Radio nice long radio
wave bar fish if you took a basketball
and
you wbp a string around it and you add
length to it how far away C basketball
and you do the same thing with the Earth
same distance you went the same distance
radio
s okay but that that was the magic of
um
that
uh Jacob
beckenstein argued and in this way
argued that
the
information that you can hide in a black
hole is proportional to its area in
plunk units the formula as it was
finally eventually
derived and I'm going to write it with
Cal
1 maybe I'll try to put the C's in wait
let's see I I no I hesitate to try to
put the C's in some they go in somewhere
but uh the entropy or the hidden
information in the black
hole is equal to the area of the
Horizon we think about building up the
uh the black hole by dropping in bit
after bit each time you add one unit of
air
area divide by
G and divide by H bar I think there's a
c cubed upstairs yeah C cubed
upstairs
okay this means the entropy of a black
hole is enormous by comparison with the
kinds of entropies in ordinary systems
of the same size you have C Cube that's
a huge number you have G and H bar which
are tiny numbers in the denominator the
entropy of a black hole is bigger than
the entrop ropy of anything else of
comparable size by a lot I mean anything
else that you ordinarily would think
about so huge numbers of bits get stored
on the surface of the black hole
proportional to the area not the volume
so the amount of information you can
keep track of in a black hole or that
needs to be kept track of is less than
you might have expected you might have
thought it was the volume of the black
hole but it's still
huge all right this is
probably one of the uh most important uh
principles of physics but yeah talking
s sorry I missed something
for yeah beckenstein had this formula
with an unknown coefficient he tried to
estimate the coefficient and he all
sorts of uh arguments but he wound up
with peculiar numbers like logarithms of
two and other things which are are not
there it's just four it was Hawking who
figured out the
four and
um good all right well let's
uh oh there are there are some
interesting there's one very interesting
thing about this formula and that's that
the H bar is in the denominator what's
the meaning of
that well you might have thought that
entropy the existence of entropy for a
black hole is a quantum mechanical
effect has something to do with quantum
mechanics and so you might think that
the entropy is proportional to Plank's
constant because it's Plank's constant
which is the measure of the quantumness
of a
system but it goes in the denominator
if Plank's constant would to get smaller
and smaller as it does in classical
physics in classical physics Plank's
constant is zero it says the entropy is
infinite that's just another way of
saying that in classical physics you can
hide since information is not quantized
it doesn't come in photons you can put
as much information into as small an
energy as you
like take an arbitrarily small amount of
energy you can put as much information
onto that wave an electromagnetic wave
as you like but in quantum mechanics
information comes in discrete
Quant um the information or the entropy
of the black hole is finite because of
quantum mechanics it would be infinite
In classical physics you could simply
throw arbitrary amounts of information
onto that black hole without increasing
in its mass by almost
anything so this is an interesting fact
that although all of this is quantum
effect it's quantum mechanics which
prevents the entropy from being too big
not the other
way it makes it
finite um what else can we say about
this well we can say a lot more about it
and we will um I think I'm getting a
little tired so we'll quck the tonight I
just can say h bar really is angular
momentum versus linear momentum so take
well har bar is simply a constant which
has certain units it has units of
angular momentum it's true but it comes
up in other quantities it has units of
action
h no it's not H over 2 pi that converts
it into no no no no no no no angular
momentum and momentum differ by a power
of a
distance angular momentum is momentum
time
distance right
momentum is H over Lambda Lambda is a
distance P * Lambda momentum times
distance as units of H
bar and P * Lambda also has units of
angular momentum r cross
P distance times
momentum okay see you next
week for more please visit us at
stanford.edu